本章我们不再讨论加密了
In this module, we're gonna stop talking
about encryption,
【伊卡酱 译注】
转而讨论信息完整性
and instead discuss message integrity.
之后我们还会回到加密，并展示如何同时提供加密和完整性
Next, we will come back to encryption, and show
how to provide both encryption and integrity.
如我所说，我们这里的目标是提供完整性，
而先不考虑私密性
So as I said, our goal here is to provide
integrity without any confidentiality.
事实上在现实中，这种情况有很多
There are actually in fact many cases in
the real world where this comes up.
例如，你可以考虑硬盘里的操作系统文件
For example, you can think of
operating system files on your disk.
如果你在使用Windows，所有的Windows操作系统文件
在硬盘上都不是私密的
Say if you're using Windows, all the Windows
operating system files on disk are not confidential,
它们是公开的，全世界都知道
they're public and known to the world,
很重要的一点是确保它们没有被病毒
或某些恶意软件修改过
but it is quite important to make sure that
they're not modified by a virus or some malware.
这就是个例子：想提供完整性
That's an example where you want
to provide integrity but you don't
但不在乎私密性。另一个例子是网页上的标签广告
care about confidentiality. Another
example is banner ads on web pages.
广告提供者不在乎有人复制
The provider of the ads doesn't care
at all if someone copies them
或向别人展示这些广告，所以没有一点私密性
and shows them to other people.
So there's no confidentiality issue at all.
但是他们很在意修改这些广告
But they do care about modifying those ads.
例如，他们希望阻止人们修改广告，
以变成不同类型的广告
So, for example, they do wanna prevent people from
changing the ads into different types of ads.
这就是另一个只关心完整性，而私密性不重要的例子
So that's another example where integrity matters
but confidentiality is not important at all.
那么我们如何提供信息的完整性？
So how do we provide message integrity?
基本的机制叫做MAC：消息验证码
The basic mechanism is what's called a MAC,
a message authentication code, MAC.
其原理如下：我们有朋友Alice和Bob
And the way we do it is as follows.
So here we have our friends, Alice and Bob.
他们共享一个密钥K，攻击者不知道K，但是双方知道
They have a shared key, K, which is not known
to the attacker, but known to both of them.
Alice想发一个公共信息M给Bob
And there's a public message M that Alice
wants to send to Bob,
并且攻击者不能在途中修改这一信息M
such that an attacker along the way cannot
modify this message on its way to Bob.
Alice的方法是使用一种叫做MAC签名算法的东西，我们记为S
The way Alice does it, is by using what's called
a MAC signing algorithm, we'll denote it by S,
MAC签名算法取密钥和信息M为输入
where the MAC signing algorithm takes
as input the key and the message,
产生一个非常短的标签。这个标签可以是
90位或100位的，等等
and produces a very short tag. The tag could
be like 90 bits or 100 bits, or so on.
尽管信息有几个G长，标签却非常短
Even though the message is gigabytes long,
the tag is actually very, very short.
然后，她把标签附在信息后面，然后把
这两个的组合发给Bob
Then, she appends the tag to the message
and sends the combination of the two to Bob.
Bob接收了消息和标签
Bob receives the message and the tag,
然后他在这个标签上运行所谓的MAC认证算法
and then he runs what's called a MAC
verification algorithm on this tag.
MAC认证算法取密钥、信息
So the MAC verification algorithm takes
as input to the key, the message,
和标签为输入，输出"是"和"否"，
取决于信息是否是有效的
and the tag and it says basically yes or no,
depending on whether the message is valid
或是被人改过。好，更精确地说
MAC是什么呢？
or whether it's been tampered with.
Okay, so more precisely, what is a MAC?
我们说过MAC包含两个算法
Well, we said the MAC basically consists of
two algorithms,
一个签名算法和一个验证算法
a signing algorithm and a verification algorithm.
通常，它们定义在一个密钥空间，一个信息空间
和一个标签空间上
As usual, they're defined over a key space,
a message space, and a tag space.
我们说过，这是一对算法
And as we said, it's a pair of algorithms.
那么签名算法会输出标签空间中的一个标签
So the signing algorithm will output a
tag in the tag space, and the verification
验证算法取密钥、信息和标签，输出是或否
algorithm, basically given the key, the
messages and the tag, will output yes or no.
文字提醒大家，通常有一致性要求
And I want to remind you as usual there are
these consistency requirements, such that
即每一个密钥空间中的密钥K和每一个信息空间中的信息
for every K in the key space and for every
message in the message space,
都正好满足，如果我使用密钥对信息进行签名
it so happens that if I sign a message
using a particular key,
然后我使用同样的密钥验证这个签名
我应该获得"是"作为回应
and then I verify the tag using the same
key, I shall get yes in response.
这是标准的一致性要求
So this is the standard consistency
requirement which is the analog of
和讨论加密时我们看过的类似
现在，我想指出
the one that we saw for encryption.
Now, one thing I'd like to point out is that
完整性确实需要Alice和Bob之间共享一个密钥
integrity really does require a shared
key between Alice and Bob.
事实上，人们有一个常犯的错误
And, in fact, there's a common mistake
that people make, where they try to
他们试图不用共享密钥就能提供完整性
这里有个例子
provide integrity without actually a
shared key. So here's an example.
考虑CRC。CRC是循环冗余检验的意思
So consider CRC. CRC stands for cyclic
redundancy check. This is a classic
是一个经典的校验和算法，为检测信息中的
随机发生的错误而设计的
checksum algorithm that's designed to
detect random errors in messages.
那么想像一下，不用密钥生成标签，Alice使用
So imagine, instead of using a key to
generate the tag, Alice basically uses a
CRC算法，是不需要任何密钥的，就能生成一个标签
CRC algorithm which is keyless. Doesn't
take any key, to generate a tag.
然后她把这个标签附在信息后面，发送给Bob
And then she appends this tag to the
message, she sends it over to Bob,
Bob会验证这个CRC码是否正确。换句话说
Bob will basically verify that the CRC is
still correct. In other words, Bob will still
Bob会检查这个标签是否等于CRC(m)
如果是，验证算法会说"是"
verify the tag is equal to CRC(m).
And if so the verification algorithm
否则验证算法会说"否"
will say yes, and otherwise the
verification algorithm will say no.
这样做的问题是，攻击者很容易就能破解之
So the problem with this is this is
very easy for an attacker to defeat.
换句话说，攻击者可以很容易地修改信息
In other words, an attacker can very easily
modify the message and route,
绕开并欺骗Bob，让他认为修改后的信息是有效的
and fool Bob into thinking that the
new message is a valid one.
攻击者的方法是取消掉标签里的信息
The way the attacker will do it
is he'll cancel the message in the tag.
他会简单地封锁它们。然后他会产生自己的信息
He'll simply block them. And then he'll
produce his own message,
M'，为信息M'计算他自己的CRC
M prime, and compute his own CRC
on this message M prime,
然后把两个联结起来发送给Bob
and then send the concatenation
of the two over to Bob.
Bob会运行验证算法，验证算法会正常工作
Bob will run the verification algorithm,
verification will work properly because
因为事实上右边是左边的有效CRC
in fact the right-hand side is in fact
a valid CRC for the left-hand side.
因此，Bob会认为这个信息来自Alice，但事实上
And as a result, Bob would think that this
message came from Alice but in fact its been
它已被攻击者修改过了，与最初的Alice发出的信息
一点关系都没有
completely modified by the attacker and had
nothing to do with the original message that Alice sent.
好，那么问题是，因为CRC没有密钥
Okay, so the problem is, because CRC
doesn't have a key, there's no difference
Alice和攻击者之间没有区别。因此
Bob不知道信息来自谁
between Alice and the attacker. And as a result,
Bob doesn't know where the message came from.
一旦我们引入了密钥，Alice就可以做一些
Bob不能做的事情了
Once we introduce a key, now Alice can do
something that the attacker can't do.
因此，她可能可以计算一个标签
而攻击者无法修改这个标签
And as a result, she might be able to compute a
tag that the attacker can't modify.
需要记住的一点是，CRC是为检测随机错误而设计的
并非针对恶意错误的
So the point to remember is that CRC is designed
to detect random errors, not malicious errors.
这里我们的目标是确保即使是一个恶意攻击者
也无法修改传递的信息
And here our goal is to make sure that even a
malicious attacker cannot modify messages in route.
接下来我们定义MAC系统安全的意义
So next we want to define what it means
for a MAC system to be secure.
通常，我们用攻击者的力量来定义安全性
攻击者可以做什么呢？
So as usual, we define security in terms of the
attacker's power. What can the attacker do?
攻击者的目标是什么？他试图做什么？
那么对于MAC的情况
And the attacker's goal. What is he trying
to do? So in the case of MACs, the
攻击者的力量是进行所谓的选择信息攻击，换句话说
attacker's power is what's called a chosen
message attack. In other words, the
攻击者可以给Alice任意他选择的信息m_1到m_q
attacker can give Alice arbitrary
messages of his choice, m_1 to m_q,
Alice会为他计算这些信息的标签，
并且给他这些算出来的标签
and Alice will compute the tag for him on
those messages, and give him those tags.
大家可能会怀疑，为什么Alice会做这些？
So again, you might wonder, why
would Alice ever do that?
为什么Alice会计算攻击者给她的信息的标签呢？
Why would Alice ever compute the tag on a
message that the attacker gave her?
就像选择明文攻击一样，这在现实中很常见的
So just like in the case of chosen plaintext
attack, it's very common in the real world,
攻击者可以给Alice一个信息，
Alice会计算这个信息的标签
that the attacker can give Alice a message.
Alice will compute the tag on that message,
然后攻击者会获得这个算出的标签
例如，攻击者可以发送给Alice一份电子邮件
and then the attacker will obtain the resulting tag.
For example, the attacker might send Alice an email.
也许Alice想把邮件保存在硬盘上，同时还想防止别人
Alice might want to save the email to
disk in a way that will prevent someone
修改硬盘上的内容。所以她会为信息计算标签
from tampering with the disk. So she'll
compute a tag on the message,
保存信息和其标签到硬盘里。
稍后，攻击者可能偷到了Alice的硬盘
and save the message and the tag to disk.
Later on, the attacker might steal Alice's disk.
现在他还原了Alice对他发送给她的信息的标签
And now he's recovered Alice's tag on the
message that he sends to Alice.
那么这就是一个真实的选择信息攻击的例子
So this is an example of a chosen message
attack in the real world, where the attacker
攻击者获得了他给Alice的信息的标签
actually obtained a tag on a
message that he gave Alice.
好，这是攻击者所能做的，即选择信息攻击
Okay, so that's what the attacker can do,
basically, this chosen message attack.
他的目标是什么？他的目标是所谓的存在性伪造
And what is his goal? Well, his goal is to do
something called an existential forgery.
攻击者试图产生某些有效的信息标签
What he's trying to do is to produce some,
some new valid message tag there.
好，某些信息标签对，不同于
Okay, so some message tag pair
that's different from one of the
在选择信息攻击里，他所获得的q个信息标签对
pairs that were given to him during
the chosen message attack.
如果他能这么做，那么我们说这个系统是不安全的
And if he can do that, then we say that
the system is insecure, and if he can't,
如果他不能，我们说这个系统是安全的。我想强调下
then we'll say the system is secure.
So I wanna emphasize this existential
存在性伪造的意思是，攻击者不能产生
一个新的信息标签对
forgery means that the attacker cannot
produce a new message/tag pair,
即使对于一个完全胡言乱语的信息也不行
大家可能会再次怀疑
even for a message that's completely gibberish.
And again, you might wonder, well,
为什么我们关心攻击者是否能计算一个
胡言乱语的信息的标签呢？
why do we care if the attacker computes
a tag on a message that's gibberish?
不是给攻击者的任何值
That's not of any value to the attacker.
但我们想构建在任何使用情况下都安全的MAC
But we want to build MACs that are
secure under any usage settings.
事实上有些实例的，比如说
你可能想计算一个随机密钥的完整性标签
And there are, in fact cases where, for example,
you might want to compute an integrity tag on
这时，即使攻击者可以计算一个完全随机的信息的标签
a random secret key. In which case, even if the
attacker is able to compute a tag on a completely
他可能可以欺骗用户去使用错误的密钥
random message, he might be able to fool
a user into using the wrong secret key.
因此我们想确保如果这个MAC是安全的
And as a result we want to make sure that
if the MAC is secure, the attacker can't
攻击者不能对任何信息产生有效的标签
无论是胡言乱语还是合理信息
produce a valid tag for any message
whether it's gibberish or sensical.
安全性定义蕴涵的另一个性质是，如果攻击者有
Another property that's implied by the security
definition is if the attacker is given some
某些信息标签对，他不应该能够对同样的信息
产生新的标签
message tag pair he shouldn't be able to
produce a new tag for the same message.
换句话说，即使对同一个信息m，
存在另一个标签t'
In other words even though there might be
another tag t' for the same message m,
给定m和t，攻击者不应该能够找到新的t'
the attacker given m and t shouldn't be able
to find this new t' and again you
大家可能又会怀疑为什么我们关心
攻击者已经有了信息M的一个标签
might wonder well why do we care the
attacker already has a tag on message M.
为什么他能否对他已经有了一个标签的信息M
产生另一标签是重要的呢？
Why does it matter if he can produce
another tag for the message M he already
我们会看到，有些应用中
has one tag? But as we'll see, there are
actually applications where it's really important
攻击者不能对已签名的信息
产生新的标签，这点是很重要的
that the attacker not to be able to produce
a new tag for a previously signed message.
特别地，当我们将加密和完整性结合起来时
这个问题就会出现
In particular, this will come up when we
combine encryption and integrity.
所以我们要求给定信息的一个标签
So that we are gonna demand that given
one tag in the message it's impossible
不可能找到同样信息的另一个标签
好，那么现在我们理解了
to find another tag for the same message.
Okay, so now that we understand the
我们试图达到的直观目标。通常
我们用一个更为精确的游戏来定义
intuition of what we are trying to achieve, let's
define it as usual using a more precise game.
这里我们有两个算法S和V，有一攻击者A
So here we have two algorithms S and V,
and we have an adversary A,
游戏如下进行：挑战者通常为MAC选择
and the game proceeds as follows.
The challenger as usual just chooses
一个随机密钥，攻击者进行他的选择信息攻击
a random key for the MAC and the adversary
basically does his chosen message attack.
那么他提交m1给挑战者，获得m1的标签
So he submits an m1 to the challenger
and receives the tag on that message m1.
然后他提交m2给挑战者，获得m2的标签
Then he submits an m2 to the challenger
and receives a tag on that m2.
等等，直到他提交了q个信息给挑战者
And so on and so forth, until, you know,
he submits Q messages to the adversary and
(口误：adversary->challenger)
获得了q个这些信息的标签
这是选择信息攻击的部分
receives Q tags on all those messages. So
that's the chosen message attack part.
然后攻击者继续试图进行存在性伪造
And then the adversary goes ahead and
tries to do an existential forgery.
他输出一个信息标签对，一个新的信息标签对
Namely, he outputs a message tag pair,
a new message tag pair.
我们说他赢下这场游戏，换句话说，b=1
意思是他赢下这场游戏
We say that he wins the game, in other words
b is equal to 1 means that he wins the game if,
如果，首先他输出的信息标签对是有效的
first of all, the message tag pair that he
outputs is a valid message tag pair,
验证算法说"是"；其次，它是一个新鲜的信息标签对
so the verification algorithm says yes.
And second of all, it's a fresh message tag pair.
换句话说，它不是之前给他的信息标签对中的任何一个
In other words, it's not one of the message
tag pairs that we gave him before.
换句话说，我们说攻击者输了这场游戏，即b=0
In other words we say that the attacker lost
the game. Namely b is equal to zero.
通常，我们定义攻击者的优势
And as usual we say, we define the advantage
of an adversary as the probability that
等于挑战者在本游戏中输出1的概率
我们说MAC系统是安全的
the challenger outputs one in this game.
We say that the MAC system is secure
对所有有效的攻击者，优势都是可忽略的。换句话说
if for all efficient adversaries the advantage
is negligible. Okay, in other words,
没有有效的攻击者可以赢得这个游戏
以不可忽略的概率
no efficient adversary can win this
game with non negligible probability.
好的，这就是安全MAC的定义
我们的目标是构建像这样的安全MAC
Alright, that's our definition of secure MACs,
and our goal is to build secure MACs like this.
在这之前，我想问大家两个问题
第一，假设我们有一个MAC
Before we do that, I wanna ask you two questions.
So the first question is, suppose we have a MAC.
攻击者正好可以找到两个信息m0和m1
And it so happens that the attacker can
find two message, m0 and m1,
它们对一半的密钥都有着同样的标签
that happen to have the same tag
for about half of the keys.
换句话说，如果你随机选择一个密钥
则以一半的概率
In other words, if you choose a key at
random with probability one half, the tag
m0的标签与m1的标签相等。我的问题是
of the message m0 will be the same as the
tag of the message m1. And my question to
这是一个安全的MAC吗？那么我想强调
you is can this be a secure MAC. So I want
to emphasize the attacker doesn't know
攻击者不知道m0和m1的标签。他只知道有一半的概率
what the tag on m0 and m1 is. All he knows
is that the two messages happen to have
这两个信息的标签是一样的
问题是，这是不是一个安全MAC
the same tag with probability one half. So
the question is whether this is a secure MAC.
答案是否定的，这不是一个安全的MAC
So the answer is no, this is not a secure
MAC and the reason is because of
原因是选择信息攻击。攻击者可以询问m0的标签
the chosen message attack. Essentially the
attacker can ask for the tag on the message
他会从挑战者那里接收到(m0,T)
事实上，T是m0的一个有效标签
m0, then he will receive m0, T from the
challenger and in fact T would be a valid
然后攻击者就可以输出他的存在性伪造(m1,T)
tag for message m0 and then what he would
output as his existential forgery is m1, T
大家注意到(m1,T)与(m0,T)不同
所以这是一个有效的存在性伪造
and you notice that m1, T is different from
m0, T, so this is a valid existential forgery.
因此，攻击者以1/2的优势能赢得这个游戏
And as a result, the attacker wins
the game with advantage one-half.
因此我们说这个MAC是不安全的。第二个问题是
So we conclude that this MAC is not secure.
The second question I'd like to ask you, is,
假设我们有一个MAC，总是输出5位标签
suppose we have a MAC that happens
to always output a five bit tag.
换句话说，这个MAC的标签空间是｛0,1｝^5
In other words, the tag space for this MAC
happens to be ｛0,1｝ to the five.
那么对每一个密钥和信息，签名算法输出5位标签
So for every key and for every message, the
signing algorithm will just output a five bit tag.
问题是，这个MAC是安全的吗？
And the question is, can this MAC be secure?
答案当然是否定的，因为攻击者可以轻松猜出标签
Of course the answer is no, because the
attacker can simply guess the tag.
攻击者根本不会进行选择信息攻击
So what he would do is he wouldn't
ask any chosen message attacks.
他会像下面这样输出存在性伪造
All he would do, is he would output
an existential forgery as follows.
他会选择一个随机标签，那么
选择一个｛0,1｝^5中的随机标签t
He would just choose a random tag. So
choose a random tag t at random in ｛0,1｝^5,
然后他就输出他的存在性伪造(m0,T)
and then he would just output his existential
forgery as say, the message zero and the tag t.
现在以概率1/2^5，这个标签是m0的一个有效标签
And now with probability of 1/2^5, this
tag will be a valid tag for the message zero.
攻击者优势是1/32，是不可忽略的
And so the adversary's advantage is
1/32, which is non-negligible.
这说明标签不能太短
So this basically says that tags
can't be too short.
它们必须有点长才行
事实上，典型的标签长度
They have to have some length to them.
And in fact, the typical tag length would be,
是64位，或96位，或128位。例如，我们使用96位长的标签
say 64 bits. or 96 bits, or 128 bits. Here let's
for example use the tags that are 96 bits long.
如果你试图去猜一个信息的标签，当标签是96位时
If you try to guess the tag for a message
when the tag is 96 bits the probability of
猜中的概率是1/2^96，攻击者的优势
guessing it correctly is 1/2^96.
So the adversary's advantage would
仅为1/2^96，是可忽略的
现在我们理解了MAC
just be 1/2^96 which is negligible.
So now that we understand what MACs are,
我想为大家展示一个简单的应用
I wanna show you a simple application.
特别地，让我们看看如何用MAC来加密硬盘上的系统文件
In particular, let's see how MACs can be
used to protect system files on disk.
那么想像一下当你安装了一个操作系统，当你安装了Windows
So imagine that when you install an operating
system, say, when you install Windows on
在你的机器上，Windows会让用户
your machine. One of the things that,
Windows does, is it asks the user for a
指定一个密码，然后根据这个密码推出一个密钥K
然后对每一个写入硬盘里的文件
password, and then derives a key K from
this password. And then for every file
这里有文件F1,F2一直到Fn
that it writes to disk, in this case, the
files would be F1, F2, up to Fn, what the
操作系统会计算文件的标签
operating system would do is it
would compute a tag for that file,
然后将标签和文件一道存放，这里把标签联结到各个文件
and then store the tag along with the file. So here
it concatenates the tag, to each one of the files.
然后它删除密钥K，他不在硬盘、内存
或任何地方存储密钥K
And then it erases the key K.
So it no longer stores the key K on disc,
好，现在设想一下，机器被病毒感染了
or on memory, or anywhere. Okay, so now
later imagine that the machine gets
病毒试图修改一些系统文件
infected with a virus and the virus tries
to modify some of the system files.
问题是用户能否检测出系统文件是否被修改了
The question is whether the user can
detect which files were modified.
这是一种方法。用户会重启机器，运行某个干净的操作系统
So here's one way to do it. Basically, the user
would reboot the machine into some clean OS.
比如从USB硬盘或其他介质重启
然后，机器从干净的操作系统重启
Say you reboot from a USB disk or something.
And then, once the machine boots from this
用户会提供给这个干净的操作系统它的密码
clean OS, the user would supply his password
to this clean running operating system.
然后这个新的干净的操作系统会检查
每个系统文件的MAC
And then this new clean running operating
system would go ahead and check the MAC for
现在，MAC是安全的，意味着
each one of the system files. Now, the
fact that the MAC is secure, means that
可怜的病毒不能创建新的文件，记为f'，以及一个有效标签
the poor virus couldn't actually create a
new file, let's call it f prime, with a valid tag.
它不能创建一个f',t'，因为如果攻击者可以这么做
So it couldn't actually create an
f′, t′. Because, if it could,
那就会是一个对这个MAC的存在性伪造了
then that would be an existential forgery
on this MAC. And because, well,
但因为这个MAC是不可被存在性伪造的
病毒不能创建任何f'
the MAC is existentially unforgeable. The
virus couldn't create any F Prime, no
无论是什么样的f'。最终，由于MAC的安全性
matter what the F Prime is. And
consequently, because of the security of
用户可以检测出所有被病毒修改过的文件
the MAC, the user will detect all the
files that were modified by the virus.
现在，这有一个警告，病毒可以做一件事
Now, there's one caveat to that. One thing
that the virus can do. Is actually swap
病毒可以交换两个文件，例如，他可以交换
这两个文件：F1和F2
two files. So, for example, he can swap
this file, file F1, with the file F2 here,
就是交换两者。那么当系统或用户
just literally swap them. So when the
system, or when the user, tries to run
试图运行F1时，他们实际是在运行F2
当然这也会造成各种损害
file F1, instead they'll be running file
F2. And of course that could cause all
防止这样做的方法就是
sorts of damage. And so the way to defend
against that is essentially by placing the
把文件名放在求MAC的区域里
事实上，我们将文件名和文件内容一起
file name inside of the MACed area, so in
fact we're computing an integrity check on
计算完整性检查。因此，如果病毒
the file name as well as on the contents
of the file. And as a result, if the virus
试图交换两个文件，系统会说，这里的文件F1
tries to swap two files, the system will
say hey, the file that's located in
不具备正确的文件名，因此会检测出
position F1 doesn't have the right name
and therefore it will detect that the virus
病毒确实交换过，尽管MAC是可以验证的
that did the swap even though the MAC
actually verifies. So it is important to
记住有一点很重要，MAC可以帮助你抵御文件篡改
或更广义上的数据篡改
remember that MACs can help you defend
against file tampering. Or data tampering
但它们无法帮助你抵御认证信息的交换
in general. But they won't help you defend
against swapping of authenticated data,
那必须借助其他方法完成，好
and that has to be done by some other
means. Okay, so that concludes our
我们对MAC的介绍先告一段落
下一节，我们开始组建
introduction to MACs, and in the next
segment, we'll go ahead and construct our
第一个安全MAC的例子
first examples of secure MACs.